<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Properties xmlns="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/custom-properties" xmlns:vt="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/docPropsVTypes"><property fmtid="{D5CDD505-2E9C-101B-9397-08002B2CF9AE}" pid="2" name="abstract"><vt:lpwstr>We use models from human behavioral ecology to examine stone artifacts from 23 sites in Korea to investigate mobility and site occupation patterns during the Late Pleistocene when new tools, such as stemmed points and blades, appeared in the archaeological record. We focus on two questions: what changes in foragers’ landscape use were associated with the introduction of new tools? And what changes in the way people use habitation sites and mobility were associated with the new technology? To answer these questions we present quantitative analyses of artifact volumetric density, retouch frequency, composition of toolkits, and artifact raw materials. We explore the environmental and demographic contexts by applying paleoclimate simulations and summed probability distribution models. We find that quartz and side scrapers, in addition to cores and choppers, remain dominant in assemblages before and after the introduction of stemmed points throughout the Late Pleistocene. Our results show that forager groups using stemmed points were associated with occupation of marginal or extreme environments. In addition, groups with stemmed points were associated with expedient technologies, indicating residential and less mobile behaviours. The environmental context of this technological innovation was a gradual decrease in temperature into the LGM. A population steadily increased before the appearance of stemmed points.</vt:lpwstr></property><property fmtid="{D5CDD505-2E9C-101B-9397-08002B2CF9AE}" pid="3" name="bibliography"><vt:lpwstr>references.bib</vt:lpwstr></property><property fmtid="{D5CDD505-2E9C-101B-9397-08002B2CF9AE}" pid="4" name="csl"><vt:lpwstr>../templates/journal-of-archaeological-science.csl</vt:lpwstr></property><property fmtid="{D5CDD505-2E9C-101B-9397-08002B2CF9AE}" pid="5" name="date"><vt:lpwstr>30 September, 2021</vt:lpwstr></property><property fmtid="{D5CDD505-2E9C-101B-9397-08002B2CF9AE}" pid="6" name="editor_options"><vt:lpwstr></vt:lpwstr></property><property fmtid="{D5CDD505-2E9C-101B-9397-08002B2CF9AE}" pid="7" name="highlights"><vt:lpwstr>These are the highlights.</vt:lpwstr></property><property fmtid="{D5CDD505-2E9C-101B-9397-08002B2CF9AE}" pid="8" name="output"><vt:lpwstr></vt:lpwstr></property></Properties>